We'll be right back.
Good to see you all this morning.
Is my mic on?
Okay.
Back on?
This is fun.
We could do this for a while.
I read online that if the pastor sees a shadow this morning, it'll be Groundhog Day.
There'll be six more weeks of this series.
Is that right?
All right.
I'm going to read you guys a story this morning of story time.
And it's a story that we have covered before.
Michelle talked about it several weeks ago, and Ryan read it when we started this series,
so it seems fitting to revisit it today.
It's the story of Paul and Silas, right?
In Acts 16, Paul and Silas, they've gone to the city of Philippi in Macedonia on a modern map
that's in the eastern arm of Greece.
And they found a community there.
They've begun to pray with this community.
They've baptized a few folks.
They've shared the gospel of Christ.
And then Luke, who's with them, records this story for us about what happens.
And we'll pick it up in verse 16, where Luke says,
As we were going to the place of prayer, we were met by a slave girl who had a spirit of divination
that brought her owners much gain by fortune-telling.
I should...
Is it not in there?
I'll just read it to you.
Okay.
My apologies.
Much gain by fortune-telling.
She followed Paul and Silas, crying out,
These men are servants of the Most High God who proclaim to you the way of salvation.
And she kept doing this for many days.
And Paul, having become greatly annoyed, turned and said to the spirit,
I command you, in the name of Jesus Christ, come out of her.
And it came out that very hour.
But when her owners saw that their hope of gain was gone,
they seized Paul and Silas and dragged them into the marketplace before the rulers.
And when they brought them to the magistrates, they said,
These men are Jews, and they're disturbing our city.
They advocate customs that are not lawful for us as Romans to accept or practice.
Made it a racial thing, right?
They're not like one of us.
The crowd joined in attacking them.
And the magistrates tore off their garments and gave orders to beat them with rods.
And when they'd inflicted many blows upon them, they threw them into prison,
ordering the jailer to keep them safely.
And having received this order, he put them in the inner prison,
and he fastened their feet in stocks.
And about midnight, Paul and Silas were praying and singing hymns to God.
And the prisoners were listening to them.
And suddenly there was a great earthquake.
So the foundations of the prison were shaken.
And immediately all the doors were opened and everyone's bonds were unfastened.
When the jailer woke and saw that the prison doors were open,
he drew his sword and was about to kill himself, supposing that his prisoners had escaped.
But Paul cried out with a loud voice,
Don't harm yourself, we're all here.
And the jailer called for lights and rushed in and trembling with fear,
he fell down before Paul and Silas.
And then he brought them out and said,
Sirs, what must I do to be saved?
And they said,
Believe in the Lord Jesus and you will be saved, you and your household.
And they spoke the word of the Lord to him, to all who were with him in his house.
And he took them that same hour of the night into his house, washed their wounds.
And he was baptized at once, he and all his family.
He brought them up into his house and set food before them.
And he rejoiced along with his entire household that he had believed in God.
Word of the Lord.
So, there are elements in that story that underline why our church,
Canvas Community Church, has the mission and vision that we do.
Okay?
And we're going to, it records Paul and Silas boldly and joyfully leading people
to reconciliation in God, right?
Like the prodigal son coming back to the father, turning around, changing his ways, coming back.
And in the midst, they're doing this in the midst of what could have been a tragic story of injustice and pain.
But somehow it wasn't in that story, which is unusual.
So, let's review our vision and mission here.
And we'll see how they map to that story.
Okay?
First of all, every church, Ryan says this all the time, every church has the same mission, right?
It's the Great Commission.
It's from Matthew 18.
It's repeated, excuse me, Matthew 28.
It's repeated in Luke 24 and in short form in Mark.
And it's repeated in Acts 1.
He tells us what?
To go into all the world, share the gospel, make disciples, baptize people into his name.
That's the mission of the church.
Bring people, reconcile them back to Christ.
Bring them back to God.
But the implementation of this mission looks very different depending on your access to
communication technology, your cultural habits, the makeup of your community, your skills,
your affluence sometimes, who you're near.
All these things can really change how you go about it, specifically how it looks.
So, what we do, of course, is we verbalize our mission.
We say, given what we have, how are we going to do this Great Commission?
What are the steps we're going to take?
And so, we verbalize it, we write it down, and that's our mission and our vision.
To get us all pointed in the same direction.
So, our vision is cultivating God's kingdom on earth by proclaiming Jesus clearly and obeying
Jesus boldly.
Now, that's what we want to see happen, right?
That's the picture.
When things work right, that's what it's going to look like.
We're going to be cultivating God's kingdom on earth by proclaiming Jesus clearly and obeying
Jesus boldly.
Our mission is what we're going to do to make that happen, right?
So, as Ryan has said, the mission, inviting real people with real lives into a Christ-centered
community, is supposed to make that picture happen.
And if you don't see how that can lead to that, you're in the right place, because that's what
we're going to talk about.
Okay?
Good.
So, our vision says, when we get it right, that's what it's going to look like.
Our mission says, we're going to be a church that invites real people into real lives,
into a Christian community, real people with real lives, which is to say, we're going to
bring people in to send them out, right?
We're bringing you in to send you out.
This is what Michelle talked about last week.
We bring folks into a Christ-centered community where they are soaked in the gospel and in
Scripture and in prayer.
And the gospel is transformational.
Transforms lives.
And people are then going out with transformed lives, as she said, with prophets, priests,
and ambassadors, notably.
We're going to talk about ambassadors today.
And this is how Paul saw it working.
Paul saw the church working this way.
And we know that because about five years after the story that we read today, he wrote
a letter to the church in Corinth after he'd been miraculously freed from prison here in
Philippi, explaining what sounds a little bit like a mission statement.
But it was at least a clear description of what they should be doing with themselves.
And I'm sorry, that's the wrong button.
They should.
So in 2 Corinthians 5, 17 to 20, he says, therefore, if anyone is in Christ, he's a new creation,
right?
That's what Michelle talked about.
Transformation power of the gospel.
You've become a new creation from having joined in Christ.
The old has passed away.
Behold, the new has come.
And all this is from God, who through Christ reconciled us to himself and gave us the ministry
of reconciliation.
He reconciled us to himself and gave us the ministry of reconciliation.
That is, in Christ, God was reconciling the world to himself, not counting the trespasses
against him, and entrusting to us that message of reconciliation.
Therefore, we are ambassadors for Christ, making his appeal through us.
We implore you, on behalf of Christ, be reconciled to God, right?
So we are cultivating—should we understand, then, that our church is an ambassador academy?
Is that what we are?
I mean, it sort of is, right?
Except that we don't have classes, we don't have requirements, we don't have fees, we don't
have—there's not a set of things you have to do to graduate, right?
What we're doing is cultivating a relationship here with the divine, which is going to lead
you to a lifestyle that's going to produce the fruit, all right?
That's how it's supposed to work.
And this was Christ's approach.
We know that because we see in the Gospels that he walked with his disciples daily for
years.
He walked with them all the way.
He let them walk with him.
They got to know each other over the course of years.
They became to know the mystery that was Christ.
And then, in Matthew 10, Mark 6, Luke 9, the Gospels record that he put them in pairs
of two and sent them out on a trial run to go see what it was like to spread the Gospel.
And what they found was that their relationship with the world had been changed.
They had been transformed by the Gospel and went out to spread it.
They had a different view of their relationship to mankind, and they were inviting them to
be reconciled.
So in some circles, there's this running debate.
Is the church a hospital?
Is this a place where you come to heal the wounded and brokenhearted?
Is this a school where you come to learn about God or morality?
Is this an outpost in the struggle against sin and evil?
Is this a worship center where we come to encounter the worship and divine?
Encounter the divine and worship him?
Our mission and vision statement says, yes, all those are true, right?
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
This is a hospital.
Our church serves all those functions in the service of bringing folks in, healing them
up, helping them grow in relationship with Christ, to get them equipped to go out and
speak clearly and obey boldly.
In fact, we're equipping them to be ambassadors of Christ, boldly and joyfully spreading the
Gospel that leads to reconciliation.
That's what the church is for.
That's what our mission and vision says.
So, cultivating God's kingdom is preparing the soil, right?
It's a farming term.
We're putting down seeds.
We're smoothing out the soil.
We're getting rid of weeds.
We're cultivating.
We're not building something.
There's no blueprint.
We're not going to have something done in six months or a year or ten years.
We're cultivating the soil so God can grow it.
And what are we growing?
God's kingdom, not ours.
When we talk frequently about not wanting to plant a new church and not wanting to build
a bigger building, it's kind of a reflection of the fact that we're not going to
that we want the kingdom of God to grow and we're not trying to build anything ourselves.
It's not the walls that matter, right?
And where are we building that?
Where are we cultivating this to grow?
We're on earth.
The implication of that is here, now, not somewhere else later.
Now.
Are we going to see the kingdom of God in its full fruition in our lifetime?
Probably not.
All Christians have wanted that.
I'd love it if it happened.
What we are going to see is growth and God working in the lives of the people that we
reach out to.
And the people that we invite in to our Christian community so that they then go out and speak
boldly and obey boldly, speak clearly and obey boldly.
So it's now, here, not Jesus.
And what are we proclaiming?
We're proclaiming Jesus, clearly.
Not a Jesus adjacent agenda.
Right?
This isn't a service.
It isn't a method of systematic morality that we're trying to pull you into or something
we're trying to get you to do.
We're just proclaiming Jesus boldly because he's going to bring the increase.
And we're obeying Jesus boldly.
Let's talk about boldly for a minute.
Paul, in the story, went to this new city, Philippi, and he proclaimed the gospel to folks
who had never heard of it.
I didn't really want to hear about it at first.
And he was there to stay indefinitely.
He was just going to stay until the job was done or God moved him on.
That is kind of bold, if you can imagine doing that.
In verse 18, he commands, with apparent expectation that it would happen, a spirit of divination
to leave this poor slave girl that it was torturing.
And that took her away from the people that were using her.
So in his annoyance, he reaches out with the love of Jesus to take this poor girl out of
her troubles.
Boldly, in front of everybody.
What if it hadn't worked?
That would be embarrassing.
He didn't even think about that, apparently.
In verse 28, he calls out to the jailer boldly.
The jailer's about to commit suicide.
He stays his hand.
That is a high-stress situation, rife with imponderables, in which Paul might have thought
it was in his interest to let the jailer just go ahead, right?
He would then be free.
He could wander off.
He wouldn't be in prison.
Michelle talked about this a few weeks ago.
Why on earth would you do what it took to make sure that your jailer stayed in control
of you?
But he didn't even think twice.
Boldly, he obeyed Christ's command to lay down his life in service of discipleship.
All right?
Verse 31, he answers clearly and immediately how the jailer might be reconciled to God when
the jailer asked him.
He boldly, clearly proclaimed the gospel.
And so please note, at no point in this story was Paul belligerent.
He was not forceful.
He was not assertive.
He was bold.
There's a difference.
He never jutted out his chin and waggled his finger and said he'd been done wrong, you
know?
He was not asserting his rightness.
He was asserting Christ's righteousness.
And he was not speaking out.
I have found that when we do that sort of self-assertive willfulness, it's from a place of insecurity
usually, right?
You're not quite sure, but you're wanting to say you are the thing you're afraid you're
not.
You're not respecting me.
I don't know if you should be, but you're not doing it.
And that's not what Paul does in any of this story.
Boldness, true unapologetic boldness that Paul had and that models for us and that we
hope to cultivate in everybody in this church is born out of confidence and a bedrock certainty.
Right?
When you go forth from this church, you will never, to speak for Jesus, it will never be
because you have a script to recite.
It'll never be because you have a set of tasks to complete or a quota to meet.
It'll be because you've experienced Christ here and you're certain both of his reality
and the need for the world's reconciliation to him.
We wouldn't ask you to assert your rightness.
You're out there to assert his righteousness.
So to act boldly like Paul did, we have to have that confidence in the living and written
word that we say we value, right?
From whence comes that confidence, right?
I'd love to have that.
Boldness comes from certainty.
Boldness comes from confidence.
Confidence comes from certainty.
What are the things in your life that you're absolutely certain about?
If you want to know about cartography, ask Mike Gabb, right?
Because he knows, he spit years in the details of cartography.
The things I think about that I know about well are the things that I've done over and over.
I've touched it.
I've felt it.
I know it inside and out.
And when you contradict me, I'm not likely to fight about it.
I'm just likely to wait until you actually have a real question and then I'll tell you about it.
All right?
If you want to know about golf, ask Ryan.
It's the thing you spend lots and lots of time with, right?
So boldness comes from confidence.
Confidence comes from certainty.
Certainty comes from familiarity.
Familiarity comes from time spent with it.
That's where the boldness comes from.
The secret to acting boldly is not willfulness.
It's not moxie.
It's not assertiveness.
It's not getting yourself worked up.
When I look back on my moments of significant boldness in my life and things I can't believe I did,
I was never trying to be bold.
I was acting out of immediate focused certainty that what I was doing was right.
And how do we develop that folks' certainty in Christ?
We spend time seeking his voice in Christian community and Scripture and in prayer,
which is why we bring you into real lives to Christ-centered community.
That's the point.
That's our mission statement.
We bring real people with real lives into Christ-centered community.
That's, I don't know where it is.
Okay.
You'll have to imagine it.
Real people with real lives into Christ-centered community
so that we can then send them out as ambassadors to Christ,
cultivating God's kingdom on earth,
contributing to the growth of a thing that's here and now that's his, not ours,
by proclaiming it clearly and obeying it boldly.
There we go.
Thank you.
Now we need to get to the vision.
So we talked about boldly.
What about proclaiming clearly?
What is it that Paul's proclaiming clearly?
Sorry, I don't know where I am in the slides here.
We've gone to the end somehow.
But what is it Paul's proclaiming clearly?
It's in this passage five times.
It says, he says, it's reconciliation, right?
That's what he's proclaiming.
Like the story of the prodigal son.
The father is waiting with open arms if you just turn around, right?
Repent, for those who don't know, means to turn.
You're walking one direction, turn and change directions.
That's what repent means.
You're going here, you realize it's the wrong way, you turn around and go this way.
In terms of reconciliation, reconciliation is etymologically to break something that's broken.
Definitionally, the way we use it, it's to heal a relationship, two people that have had a rift.
Two groups that can no longer communicate.
You want to reconcile them together.
Christ, the gospel of reconciliation is you're resisting God.
You're moving away from God.
You think he's fighting you because you're fighting him, right?
Someone tells you there's a gospel, you should repent, you should turn.
Go back to God.
And when you do, you see he's standing there with open arms wanting to welcome you.
In the story of the prodigal son.
C.S. Lewis.
So, yeah, so step one then is making, step one of making our vision a reality is engendering boldness by immersion,
immersing ourselves in prayer, Scripture, and Christian community, which deepens daily our relationship with God.
And step two, knowing how to proclaim, that really comes out of the same thing, right?
Paul and Silas did, when they were reconciled with God, see that they were endowed with a ministry of reconciling others.
That's why, in that moment of stress, they were most focused on and most excited about the jailer hearing the gospel.
Because that was their focus.
And we see that that was more important to Paul and Silas than their justice, they definitely had been treated unjustly,
than their freedom, they didn't try to get away, or their safety even.
They weren't focused on any of those things, they were focused on his eternal safety, reconciliation with God.
And, as a parenthetical note, that led Paul and Silas to build a church which became their primary backers through the rest of Paul's ministry.
They really stood by him when everything was going down.
And this was the bedrock that he, church, that he really first got his ministry on solid feet.
So, C.S. Lewis says it this way.
In Mere Christianity, which, by the way, I've said before, top five books that every Christian should read.
This is the top of my list.
If you haven't read it, please go buy it and read it, Mere Christianity.
He says in there,
Fallen man is not simply an imperfect creature who needs improvement.
We haven't just sinned.
He's a rebel who must lay down his arms.
We've sinned and we're resisting God.
So, the people out there who are resisting this God, whose image they bear, it seems insane to them to say,
Just repent, turn around, go back to the guy you're fighting.
Right?
That's why you need the ambassadors to go out on his behalf and say, please be reconciled.
Please repent.
To explain this to them.
And when I say them, it was all of us, presumably.
Right?
We're rebels that must lay down our arms.
When we're actively running and struggling, we can't tell what the right direction is, but like the father and the prodigal son, we see him there with arms open, wanting to welcome back the one who bears his image, his son.
That's us.
Now, some of you may be skeptical about that.
And some of the people you talk to may be skeptical about that.
That claim that church seeks reconciliation and relationship because they have experience and because they've read the Bible.
Right?
And in their experience, a church is full of rules and they've read the Bible and it has, what, the Ten Commandments?
At first blush, without thinking it through, that does not sound like a list of how to reconcile, although I would argue that it is.
But it doesn't sound that way.
Right?
They've attended unending Sunday school classes, maybe as children, where they were told to be kind, love one another, all these really good things, but they're a list of rules, things you're supposed to do.
How's that a relationship, they say.
In many of the New Testament letters, 1 Peter 3 and 4 is two complete chapters of just a list of how you should behave.
Right?
And you've read that.
So you say, how is this, is this, is this really a mystical relationship you're asking me into or is this an ethical requirement?
Is this a series of ethical worldview?
Is it a behavioral list?
And to answer that, I would like to refer you all to the expectations that we place on marriage.
Okay?
There are a set of ethical behaviors we expect from our spouse, kindness, faithfulness, reliability, others.
And surely, these are expressions of, evidence of, love and devotion.
Right?
They're not because marriage vows present us with a list of onerous responsibilities.
Faithfulness is evidence of love, we think.
It also sounds, it's also grounds for more confidence in that love.
So I would just like you to raise your hand publicly if you think it's reasonable to ask your spouse, is this a relationship or a list of ethical responsibilities?
No.
Okay.
No takers.
Because we know the behavior is an outflow of the evidence of the committed relationship.
Right?
We hear what God says and we act on it as part of understanding him.
That's what the Hebrew word shema is, to hear and obey.
To hear is to obey.
Christ explains that to his New Testament audience with the parable of the house on the solid ground versus sand.
You hear my words, you do them, it's like building your house on a rock, it'll stay there.
You hear my words, you don't do them, it's like building your house on sand, you might as well not have built it.
Right?
To hear is to obey.
You can't do one without the other.
And now, there are times though, speaking in terms of your spouse, when despite knowing how much your spouse loves you,
they don't behave the way you would expect them to or that you would like them to.
And I'm sure we've all experienced that, not just with spouses, but siblings and employers and parents.
And we say, where's the evidence of relationship here?
Right?
Now, of course, if relationships are functioning the way they should, if you're functioning the way you should in a relationship,
we look at ourselves, not at the other person, right?
And we say, where's the evidence?
Does my behavior square with the expected outcome of this relationship?
Am I being kind?
Am I being faithful?
Am I being reliable?
And it's that need for self-reflection, for healthy relationship, that evaluation of how our behaviors look and what they mean about us.
That's what leads the New Testament authors to give us those lists of poor and preferred behaviors.
They're evaluating themselves.
They're evaluating their churches.
And John makes this explicitly clear in Revelation 2, 4, and 5.
He says, but I have this against you that you've left your first love.
Right?
Therefore, remember from where you've fallen and repent and do the deeds you did at first.
Okay?
He correlates first love with first behavior.
He's calling the church to be reconciled with their first love.
And the need for that reconciliation is indicated by their behaviors, which is manifestly clear in the parable of the prodigal son we read.
Right?
He needed to reconcile.
You could tell from his behavior.
And to mix a metaphor, in John 10, 27, he says, my sheep hear my voice and follow me.
That's trust and devotion that a sheep have leads to expected behaviors, even in sheep.
Right?
You don't have to be an adult human.
Everybody who has trust and devotion will act on that.
They hear and obey and are reconciled once again to the shepherd that they're running away from.
If you've ever kept sheep, it happens over and over.
They get scared in a herd mentality and take off and you have to call them and they're like, oh, right, that makes sense.
I like him.
I trust him.
And they come back.
Right?
Over and over.
The need for reconciliation occurs to them when they hear the voice of the one they've come to know and trust.
So to practically fulfill our vision of cultivating, proclaiming, and boldly obeying, we must come to know his voice through spending time with him.
Because we, sheep-like, are easily distracted.
We're easily frightened.
We're easily stampeded in a herd mentality when you hear something mildly frightening on the internet.
And we have to constantly immerse ourselves, our real lives, in prayer and Scripture and Christian community.
And that means you cannot leave your life at home and come spend an hour here and then go back to your real life.
You bring your life and immerse it in Christian community, living in the circles, so that it's affected.
It's transformed by the renewing of your mind.
The gospel has a transformative effect on you, if you bring yourself to the gospel.
And spouse-like, we need the certainty that comes from familiarity to develop that attached disregard, that sort of deafness to the things that distract us from our first love.
And we do this all with joy.
Right?
We proclaim Jesus' gospel of reconciliation clearly, and we obey him boldly.
And when we do, it shouldn't feel like a job.
Paul and Silas were singing in prison, right?
Looking back at the story, that whole story is driven by joy, which doesn't make any sense because it's a story of injustice and torture and imprisonment.
And even an earthquake.
Earthquakes aren't good, right?
We read it in that story as if a great thing happened to them, but they had to sit through an earthquake while chained up inside a stone building.
That would have been disconcerting.
But they're joyful as they're sitting in stocks in the inner prison, having been beaten and unjustly tried, waiting for a kangaroo court in the morning, right?
They weren't self-absorbed by their troubles.
They weren't absorbed by their own considerations.
Because why?
What gave them the joy?
Dietrich Bonhoeffer was the leader of the confessing church in Germany during World War II.
The fascist Nazi party had taken over the church.
To be a legal church and not be shut down, you had to commit to the Nazi party and their line.
Most churches went along with this.
The Catholic church didn't.
And the confessing church, led by Bonhoeffer, a series of churches, didn't.
And so he was trying to live out Christian community under the thumb of Hitler, right?
That's a guy who knows a little bit about trial and tribulation.
And he famously wrote this sermon in the midst, delivered this sermon to his congregation in the midst of this situation.
When, how do you function as a Christian when a fascist government is taking over the story of the gospel?
Well, he said, he likened his church to the disciples when they were in the boat on the sea and Jesus came and calmed the storm.
But he didn't talk about calming the storm.
He talked about being in the boat on the sea with Christ in the boat with them.
Right?
We're in the boat, Christ in the boat, the storm's outside.
Why would you want to be outside?
This is where you want to be, he said.
The joy is from being with Christ in the boat, independent of the waves.
That's from a man who was going through it, right?
And this is what we see with Paul and Silas.
In verse 28, Paul was able to stay aware of the people around him.
And as we said, act against his apparent self-interest by stopping the jailer from harming himself because he wasn't focused on his troubles.
He was focused on seeing the image of God in others as God sees them.
And he was able to do that because he was living in this Christian community, immersed in prayer, immersed in Scripture, immersed in holding one another up.
He was acting in joy, detached from circumstance, and he was able to see the world and the people in it as Christ does.
And so that's why he could care for others despite his troubles.
And in verse 34, notably, I love this, the passage ends with what?
The jailer rejoicing, right?
The jailer ends this in joy too.
He'd had a rough day.
His prison fell down.
His prisoners, you know, first of all, he'd been told to imprison this guy that didn't seem like something was right about this trial, but he's doing his job.
Then his prison gets knocked down, and then he's afraid the prisoners are going to escape.
He's had a bad day.
But he hears the gospel.
And from that, he washes the wounds of the prisoners.
He invites them into his house.
He falls down before them in giving them honor.
It's unheard of.
And it ends with rejoicing.
He's greatly rejoicing because he has the gospel now in his life.
So from when comes this joy?
C.S.
Lewis, again, in Mere Christianity, says that when he found, he wrote a lot about joy.
He wrote a whole second book called Surprised by Joy.
He said he found in himself a desire for which no experience in the world could satisfy this desire.
And he found that the most probable explanation was that he wasn't made for this world.
He was made for another world.
He was made in the image of God, and he was longing for a better place.
He was longing for and looking forward with expectant hope to the time when he would know his real world.
That sounds escapist, but it was real.
Yesu, joy of man's desiring, desiring box great few, right?
That was an expression of, his expression of, the desiring for Jesus that goes beyond the troubles of this world.
Paul says it.
Joy comes from hope, hope comes from longing, and as Paul says, we have a hope that does not disappoint.
Christ embodied this joy.
Ryan talked about it a few weeks ago when he said Christ came eating and drinking with radical hospitality,
inviting the sinners to eat with him and know him.
The ambassadorial tasks for which this church will prepare you, if we stay on mission,
are not bullet points or check boxes.
The tasks should all flow out of the persons we're becoming, which is naturally.
The boldness comes from familiarity, clarity comes from preparation,
and the joy comes from this new perspective that the jailer had.
It's not a byproduct.
It's not happiness.
It's not getting what you want.
In Colossians 3.
Oh, that one was up there.
There it is.
In Colossians 3, 15 to 17, Paul says,
Let the peace of Christ to which you were indeed called in one body rule your hearts and be thankful.
Let the word of God richly dwell in you with all wisdom and teaching,
admonishing one another with psalms and hymns and spiritual songs,
singing with thankfulness in your heart.
This is a picture of joy couched in the language of gratitude.
Whatever you do in word or deed, do everything in the name of the Lord Jesus,
giving thanks to him through God the Father.
Thanks for what?
For the reconciliation.
It's a picture of joy, joyful living, rooted in thankfulness for the reconciliation that God has provided through Jesus' sacrificial act.
Him reconciling us to God.
And this is how we, how Paul, how Silas, how all our friends in here,
who are going through rough times right now,
are celebrating through the trouble.
We're in fellowship.
We're fellows in the ship with Christ, as Bonhoeffer pictured it.
And we're looking on him with gratitude, not on the storm outside the ship with fear.
We're living in a real hope that does not disappoint.
Our vision, then, is that we will share this hope,
invite others into this hope,
and that will be the catalyst for that reconciliation.
That's all based in joy.
But our first mission is to invite others into Christ-centered community to live in that hope with us.
And you have to ask yourself, when you say this to them,
am I asking them to live in the delusion, like hope something happens?
How is that something to base your life on?
Because it's not hoping it'll happen.
We use the word hope as something that will clearly not happen.
A negative vanity.
But in the scriptural sense, hope is the certainty of the promise to come.
Paul addresses, in 1 Corinthians 15, he says,
if Christ hadn't been raised, then we are, of all the people, most to be pitied.
Gospel's void.
Some translations say we're the most miserable of all people.
But in Romans 5, 5,
Paul addresses this.
We celebrate in the hope of glory of God.
The hope of the glory of God.
The impending glory of him.
And not only this, but we also celebrate in our tribulations,
knowing that tribulation brings about perseverance.
This is the guy who said, this was written shortly after he'd been sitting in the prison, by the way, right?
Tribulation brings about perseverance.
Perseverance brings about proven character.
Proven character brings about hope.
And that hope does not disappoint.
Because the love of God has been poured out within our hearts through the Holy Spirit who was given to us.
So, in summary,
Paul and Silas are an image of what it looks like to be ambassadors of Christ.
If you hadn't gotten that yet.
As Michelle said last week, their lives were transformed by the gospel.
So they were boldly and joyfully spreading the gospel that leads to reconciliation.
And as Ryan outlined a few weeks ago,
they also knew from Christ's warnings and from their own painful experience in this story
that some people would not understand, wouldn't take it well, right?
They were beaten.
They were thrown in prison.
Some will be offended.
And that's okay.
We're not trying to build something.
We're just cultivating.
We're just planting seeds.
We're just preparing the soil.
Rejection doesn't mean failure.
Rejection means it hasn't grown yet.
These are not tasks.
This is a lifestyle of obedience.
In 1966, Thomas Merton,
he's a monk and an author, very much worth reading.
He wrote to a young man who was becoming weary in his well-doing.
And Merton said,
Do not depend on the hope of results.
When you're doing the sort of work that you've taken on,
essentially an apostolic work,
you may have to face the fact that you will be apparently worthless
and achieve no results at all.
And as you get used to this,
gradually, as you struggle less and less for an idea
and more and more for specific people,
it gets much more real.
All the good that you will do will come not from you,
but from the fact that you've allowed yourself in obedience to faith
to be used by God's love.
Think of this more and gradually you'll be freed from your need to prove yourself.
You'll never go out assertively.
You'll only speak boldly of the love of Christ that you know.
We just want to make room for people, right?
In our Christ-centered lives, we want to make room for conversation.
We're not anxiously, hurriedly building something.
We're cultivating the ground.
Cultivate means God does the work in response to our participation.
So, in 2025, we will invite folks, as they are,
into real Christ-centered community here
to spend time with us in Scripture and in prayer
because we want the gospel to engender things in them.
We want it to engender familiarity that breeds certainty,
that leads to boldness.
We want it to engender clarity that comes from understanding,
that comes from preparation,
a clarity of understanding that comes from preparation
and joy that comes from the perspective of thankfulness
that imbues everything we do.
And when that happens,
this church can then impact the world outside our walls
by cultivating God's kingdom on earth,
by proclaiming Jesus clearly and obeying him boldly.
Let's pray.
Father God, I thank you.
Thank you so much that everybody's been brought here together
that are here.
Those that are going through trouble,
pray that we can reach out to them
and express the love of God to them
and with them, for them.
That we would be ambassadors for you
speaking the word of reconciliation
as we, like sheep, like day after day,
kind of pull away from you
and forget our first love.
Let us bring ourselves back.
Let us hear your voice.
Let us immerse ourselves
in the community and in Scripture and prayer
that will let us know you more.
In Jesus' name, amen.